A Guide to the Gilliam Family Papers 1802-1932
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Gilliam Family Papers 1802-1932
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2608
This collection consists of ca. 1500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Gilliam Family Papers were purchased from Miss Jane Davis, P.O. Box 765, Petersburg, Va. on February 12, 1947.
Scope and Content Information
The Gilliam Family Papers, 1802-1932, consist of ca. 1500 items (ca. 2 shelf feet) primarily pertaining to personal family correspondence, various accounts and bills, and political correspondence. These papers are grouped into the following categories: accounts, receipts; personal and family correspondence; slave trade papers; political correspondence.
The accounts and receipts, including various bills, etc., chronicle the daily financial activities of the family. They include indentures and a series of rent agreements made by Samuel Y. Gilliam during 1896- 1900. During the pre-Civil War period the accounts pertain to the operation of a farm or plantation. The personal and family papers are concentrated in the post 1850 years. The papers relating to slavery cover the years 1828-1865 and include the hiring out of slaves, trading of slaves, purchases, slavery accounts, and general papers revealing the daily involvement with the institution. The political correspondence is concentrated in the 1870-1899 period and centered on the activities of Samuel Gilliam.
Although historically obscure, the Gilliam family had a long and fruitful association with Dinwiddie County. John W. Gilliam was the most prominent memeber of the family until his death in 1853. He and his wife Mary Eppes Gilliam had four children. Joseph P., John W., and Samuel Y. Gilliam all appear subsequently in the family papers. The papers prior to 1853 are receipts, bills, accounts that indicate Gilliam's activities in running his farm. His name and that of his son Joseph P. Gilliam dominate the slavery papers. John Gilliam also represented Dinwiddie County in the state House of Delegates during 1847-1848 and vigorously criticized the Mexican War (see family papers 3593-a). Upon his death his wife Mary Eppes Gilliam carried on the family affairs and her name appears frequently in the accounts and correspondence during the 1850's and 1860's. There is surprisingly little material concerning the Civil War. But by 1866 the family was "heavily indebted," possibly as a consequence of the ravages of war.
Samuel Y. Gilliam dominates the family papers during 1870-1899. There is important political correspondence contained in the papers of these years. In 1877 he sought to represent Dinwiddie County in the legislature but was defeated. Subsequently, however, he became a leader of the "readjustor" party and by 1896 was described as the "leader of the Republican Party" in the county. In 1899 he was elected county treasurer. His letters are quite interesting, discussing candidly political maneuvering and the need to gain the votes of blacks to control county politics.
The latter portion of the papers, from 1901-1932, contain correspondence adn miscellaneous financial records such as tax receipts. They pertain chiefly to Rosa Boisseau, a cousin of the Gilliams, about whom little is known.
Organization
There are four topical groupings within a chronological arrangement. They include: accounts, receipts, bills, etc.; personal and family correspondence, slavery papers (three folders 1828-1861); and political correspondence. The accounts and receipts are arranged chronologically only by year while the other subdivisions are month by month and day by day.
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Material
This collection is related to subsequent purchases of the Gilliam Papers in 1949, 1950, and 1952. These collateral collections are: #3164, which contains indentures and miscellaneous correspondence for 1794-1913; #3593, which contains military commissions and miscellaneous correspondence for 1839-1905; #3593-a, which included various correspondence for 1840-1884. #3595-a also contains the speeches of John W. Gilliam against the Mexican War delivered as a delegate for Dinwiddie County.
Contents List
- Deed 1802-1805 (Box 1)
- Estate listing 1817 (Box 1)
- Gilliam Estate listing, Copy of Will 1823-1827 (Box 1)
- Indentures, Accounts 1828-1829 (Box 1)
- Accounts, Courts and debt papers 1830-1833 (Box 1)
- Accounts, Promises to pay 1834-1837, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Accounts, Receipts, Indenture 1838-1839 (Box 1)
- Receipts 1840-1842 (Box 1)
- Military Commissions 1842-1843 (Box 1)
- Accounts, Receipts 1843-1844, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence 1844 (Box 1)
- Accounts, Receipts 1845-1849, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Personal and Business letters 1848-1849 (Box 1)
- Accounts, Receipts 1850 (Box 2)
- Business and Family letters 1850 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts 1851 (Box 2)
- Business and Miscellaneous letters 1851 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts 1852 (Box 2)
- Family and Business letters, Sale Bill 1852 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts 1853 (Box 2)
- Family and Business letters 1853 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts 1854 (Box 2)
- Family and Personal letters 1854 (Box 2)
- Business and Family letters 1855 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, Promises to pay 1856 (Box 2)
- Family and Personal letters 1856 (Box 2)
- Political Correspondence 1855-1856 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts 1857 (Box 2)
- Personal and Family Correspondence, Court matter 1857 (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts, Bills 1858 (Box 2)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1858 (Box 2)
- Slavery Trade papers 1828-1861, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Accounts, Receipts, Bills 1859 (Box 3)
- Family and Personal Correspondence 1859 (Box 3)
- Acconts, Receipts, Bills 1860 (Box 3)
- Family and Personal Correspondence 1860 (Box 3)
- Accounts, Receipts, Bills 1861 (Box 3)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1861 (Box 3)
- Accounts, Receipts, Bills 1862 (Box 3)
- Personal Correspondence and Papers re Confederate Army Forces 1862 (Box 3)
- Accounts, Receipts, Bills 1863 (Box 3)
- Personal Correspondence and Family letters 1863 (Box 3)
- Accounts, Bills, Receipts 1864-1865 (Box 3)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1864-1865, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Accounts, Receipts, Bills, Bankruptcy Certificate 1866-1868 (Box 3)
- Personal Correspondence 1866-1868 (Box 3)
- Accounts, Bills, Receipts 1869-1873 (Box 4)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1869-1873 (Box 4)
- Accounts, Bills, Receipts 1874-1880 (Box 4)
- Personal, Political and Family papers 1874-1880 (Box 4)
- Accounts, Receipts, Miscellaneous 1881-1886 (Box 4)
- Personal, Political and Family papers 1881-1886 (Box 4)
- Accounts, Receipts, Miscellaneous 1887-1890 (Box 4)
- Personal, Family and Political papers 1887-1890 (Box 4)
- Political papers and Correspondence 1873-1899 (Box 4)
- Accounts, Receipts, Rent Agreements, Miscellaneous 1891-1892 (Box 4)
- Personal Correspondence 1891-1892 (Box 4)
- Accounts, Receipts, Rent Agreements, Miscellaneous 1893-1895 (Box 4)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1893-1895 (Box 4)
- Rent Agreements, Miscellaneous Accounts, Receipts 1896-1897 (Box 5)
- Personal, Family, Miscellaneous Correspondence 1896-1897 (Box 5)
- Rent Agreements 1898-1900 (Box 5)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1898-1900 (Box 5)
- Accounts, Deeds, Contracts 1901-1917 (Box 5)
- Personal and Family Correspondence 1901-1917 (Box 5)
- Tax receipts and bank notes 1920-1932 (Box 5)
- Personal Correspondence 1920-1926 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 5)
- Notebook n.d. (Box 5)